<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>

<chapter id="decorators">
  <title>Decorators</title>
  
  <para>Interceptors are a powerful way to capture and separate concerns
  which are <emphasis>orthogonal</emphasis> to the type system. Any
  interceptor is able to intercept invocations of any Java type. This makes
  them perfect for solving technical concerns such as transaction management
  and security. However, by nature, interceptors are unaware of the actual
  semantics of the events they intercept. Thus, interceptors aren't an
  appropriate tool for separating business-related concerns.</para>
  
  <para>The reverse is true of <emphasis>decorators</emphasis>. A decorator
  intercepts invocations only for a certain Java interface, and is therefore
  aware of all the semantics attached to that interface. This makes decorators
  a perfect tool for modeling some kinds of business concerns. It also 
  means that a decorator doesn't have the generality of an interceptor. 
  Decorators aren't able to solve technical concerns that cut across many
  disparate types.</para>
  
  <para>Suppose we have an interface that represents accounts:</para>
  
<programlisting><![CDATA[public interface Account {
    public BigDecimal getBalance();
    public User getOwner();
    public void withdraw(BigDecimal amount);
    public void deposit(BigDecimal amount);
}]]></programlisting>

  <para>Several different Web Beans in our system implement the 
  <literal>Account</literal> interface. However, we have a common legal 
  requirement that, for any kind of account, large transactions must be 
  recorded by the system in a special log. This is a perfect job for a
  decorator.</para>
  
  <para>A decorator is a simple Web Bean that implements the type it
  decorates and is annotated <literal>@Decorator</literal>.</para>
  
<programlisting><![CDATA[@Decorator
public abstract class LargeTransactionDecorator 
        implements Account {
    
    @Decorates Account account;
    
    @PersistenceContext EntityManager em;
    
    public void withdraw(BigDecimal amount) {
        account.withdraw(amount);
        if ( amount.compareTo(LARGE_AMOUNT)>0 ) {
            em.persist( new LoggedWithdrawl(amount) );
        }
    }
    
    public void deposit(BigDecimal amount);
        account.deposit(amount);
        if ( amount.compareTo(LARGE_AMOUNT)>0 ) {
            em.persist( new LoggedDeposit(amount) );
        }
    }
    
}]]></programlisting>

  <para>Unlike other simple Web Beans, a decorator may be an abstract 
  class. If there's nothing special the decorator needs to do for a 
  particular method of the decorated interface, you don't need to 
  implement that method.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Delegate attributes</title>
  
    <para>All decorators have a <emphasis>delegate attribute</emphasis>. 
    The type and binding types of the delegate attribute determine which
    Web Beans the decorator is bound to. The delegate attribute type must
    implement or extend all interfaces implemented by the decorator.</para>
    
    <para>This delegate attribute specifies that the decorator is bound to
    all Web Beans that implement <literal>Account</literal>:</para>
    
<programlisting><![CDATA[@Decorates Account account;]]></programlisting>

    <para>A delegate attribute may specify a binding annotation. Then the
    decorator will only be bound to Web Beans with the same binding.</para>
    
<programlisting><![CDATA[@Decorates @Foreign Account account;]]></programlisting>

    <para>A decorator is bound to any Web Bean which:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>has the type of the delegate attribute as an API type, and</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>has all binding types that are declared by the delegate attribute.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>The decorator may invoke the delegate attribute, which has much the same
    effect as calling <literal>InvocationContext.proceed()</literal> from an
    interceptor.</para>
  
  </section>
  
<section>
  <title>Enabling decorators</title>

  <para>We need to <emphasis>enable</emphasis> our decorator in 
  <literal>web-beans.xml</literal>.</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<Decorators>
    <myapp:LargeTransactionDecorator/>
</Decorators>]]></programlisting>

  <para>This declaration serves the same purpose for decorators that the
  <literal>&lt;Interceptors&gt;</literal> declaration serves for interceptors:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>it enables us to specify a total ordering for all decorators 
      in our system, ensuring deterministic behavior, and</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>it lets us enable or disable decorator classes at deployment time.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist> 

  <para>Interceptors for a method are called before decorators that apply to
  that method.</para>

</section>
  
</chapter>