<!DOCTYPE part PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<part id="part-1">
   
   <title>Architecture of Weld-OSGi</title>
   
   <chapter>
      <title>Framework organisation</title>
      <para>Weld-OSGi is composed of five bundles: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>The <emphasis>API bundle</emphasis> that describes the programming model and the OSGi extension
                  mechanism.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>The <emphasis>SPI bundle</emphasis> that describes the CDI implementatio hooking mechanism.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>The <emphasis>third party API bundle</emphasis> that provides all the needed third party
                  API.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>The <emphasis>extension bundle</emphasis> that extends the OSGi environment by managing bean
                  bundles,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>The <emphasis>integration bundle</emphasis> that provides OSGi ready Weld containers to the
                  extension bundle.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist></para>
      <para>Note that as Weld-OSGi runs in an OSGi environment it is implicit
         that there is an OSGi core bundle too. This one provide OSGi features for all other bundles, including bean
         bundles. But it is not an actual part of Weld-OSGi.</para>
      <figure>
         <title>The five bundles of Weld-OSGi</title>
         <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
               <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" depth="800" fileref="../images/5Bundles.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>This figure shows the five bundles of Weld-OSGi and the links between them.</caption>
         </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>These bundles could regroup in two part (as shown in the figure above):<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>Extension part: this part represents the actual OSGi extension. It detects and manages bean bundles
                  and provides the programming model. This part is more described in chapter 2.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Integration part: this part represents the Weld integration. It provides all the Weld containers
                  needed by the extension part and defines how these containers should hookup with bean bundles. This
                  part is more described in chapter 3.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>The third party API bundle : this bundle does not actually belong to a part.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist></para>
   </chapter>
   
   <chapter>
      <title>Extension part</title>
      <section>
         <title>API bundle</title>
         <para>The extension API defines all the features provided to OSGi
            environment using CDI specification. It exposes all the new utilities and defines the comportment of the
            extension bundle.</para>
         <para>It exposes all the interfaces, events and annotations usable by a developers in order to develop its
            client bean bundles. It defines the programming model of bean bundle. Mostly it is about publishing and
            consuming injectable services in a CDI way.</para>
         <para>It also describes the object the extension bundle needs to
            orchestrate bean bundles.</para>
         <para>So this is where to search for new usages of OSGi.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Extension bundle: the puppet master</title>
         <para>The extension bundle is the orchestrator of Weld-OSGi. It may be use by any application that requires
            Weld-OSGi. It may be just started at the beginning of a Weld-OSGi application. It requests the extension API
            bundle as a dependency.</para>
         <para>The extension bundle is the heart of Weld-OSGi applications. Once it is started, provided that it finds a
            started integration bundle, it manages all the bean bundles. It is in charge of service automatic
            publishing, service injections, CDI event notifications and bundle communications.</para>
         <para>It runs in background, it just need to be started with the OSGi environment, then everything is
            transparent to the user. Client bean bundles do not have to do anything in order to use Weld-OSGi
            functionality.</para>
         <para>In order to perform injections the extension bundle search for a CDI compliant container service provider
            once it is started. Thus it can only work coupled with a bundle providing such a service: the integration
            bundle.</para>
         <para>The extension bundle provides an extension to OSGi as an
            extender pattern. The extension bundle, the extender, tracks for bean bundles, the extensions, to be
            started. Then CDI utilities are enabled for these bean bundles over OSGi environment.</para>
         <para>The extension bundle works that
            way:<programlisting>BEGIN
    start
    WHILE ! integration_bundle.isStarted
        wait
    END_WHILE
    obtain_container_factory
    FOR bean_bundle : started_bundles
        manage_bean_bundle
        provide_container
    END_FOR
    WHILE integration_bundle.isStarted
        wait_event
        OnBeanBundleStart
            manage_bean_bundle
            provide_container
        OnBeanBundleStop
            unmanage_bean_bundle
    END_WHILE
    stop
    FOR bean_bundle : namaged_bundles
        unmanage_bean_bundle
        stop_bean_bundle
    END_FOR
END</programlisting></para>
         <para>So this is where the magic happens and where OSGi applications
            become much more simple.</para>
      </section>
   </chapter>
   
   <chapter>
      <title>Integration part</title>
      <section>
         <title>SPI bundle</title>
         <para>The SPI bundle defines how a CDI container, such as Weld, should bootstrap with the extension bundle. So
            any CDI environment implementation could be used by the extension bundle transparently. The CDI compliant
            container may be provided using an integration bundle.</para>
         <para>This aims at providing the minimum integration in order to
            start a CDI compliant container with every managed bean bundle. Then the extension bundle can get a CDI
            container to provide to every one of its manages bean bundle.</para>
         <para>Moreover the integration API allows to mix CDI compliant
            container in the same application by providing an embedded mode. In this mode a bean bundle is decoupled
            from the extension bundle and is managed on its own. Thus various implementations of CDI container can be
            used or the behavior of a particular bean bundle can be particularized.</para>
         <para>All this bootstrapping mechanism works using the service layer of OSGi. A CDI compliant integration
            bundle may provide a service that allows the extension bundle to obtain a new container for every bean
            bundle.</para>
         <para>So this is where to search to make Weld-OSGi use a specific CDI compliant container.</para>
         
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>Integration bundle: provide Weld containers</title>
         <para>The integration bundle is responsible for providing Weld containers to the extension bundle. It may be
            started with the extension bundle and publish a CDI container factory service. It request the integration
            API bundle as a dependency.</para>
         <para>The integration bundle may work that way:</para>
         <programlisting>BEGIN
    start
    register_container_factory_service
    WHILE true
        wait
        OnContainerRequest
            provide_container
    END_WHILE
    unregister_container_factory_service
END</programlisting>
      </section>
   </chapter>
   
   <chapter>
      <title>Weld-OSGi features</title>
      
      <para> As an extension to OSGi, Weld-OSGi provides several features : <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>Complete integration with OSGi world by the use of extender pattern and extension bundle. Thus
                  complete compatibility with already existing tools.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Non intruding, configurable and customizable behavior in new or upgraded application. Simple
                  configuration and usage with annotations, completely xml free.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Full internal CDI support for bean bundles: injection, producers, interceptors, decorators
                  ...</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Lot of ease features for OSGi usages: injectable services, event notifications, inter-bundle
                  communication ...</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>OSGi and CDI compliance all along the way ensuring compatibility with all CDI compliant container
                  and easy application realisation or portage.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist></para>
   </chapter>
   
   <chapter>
      <title>Weld-OSGi workflow</title>
      <figure>
         <title>Weld-OSGi framework start and stop protocol</title>
         <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
               <imagedata format="PNG" align="center" width="800" depth="600" fileref="../images/StartStopProtocol.png"
               />
            </imageobject>
            <caption>This figure shows the steps of the Weld-OSGi starting and stopping protocol. Between step 8 and
               step 11 the framework is in stable state and manages bean bundles.</caption>
         </mediaobject>
      </figure>
   </chapter>
   
   <chapter>
      <title>Bean bundles life cycle</title>
      <para>This section presents the lifecycle of a bean bundle and how it
         impacts CDI and OSGi regular behaviors. Mostly bean bundles follow the same lifecycle than a regular bundle.
         There are only two new possible states and they do not modify the behavior from OSGi side.</para>
      <figure>
         <title>The bean bundle lifecycle</title>
         <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
               <imagedata align="center" format="PNG" depth="800" fileref="../images/BeanBundleLifeCycle.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>This figure shows the two new states a bean bundle can be in. These states are triggered by two new
               events and address the CDI container dependency resolution (i.e. services annotated @Required).</caption>
         </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The regular OSGi lifecycle is not modified by the new Weld-OSGi states as they have the same meaning than
         the ACTIVE state from an OSGi point of view. They only add information about the validation of required service
         availability.</para>
   </chapter>
   
   <chapter>
      <title>Bean bundle characteristics</title>
      <para>There are very few things to do in order to obtain a bean bundle
         from a bean archive or a bundle. Mostly it is just adding the missing marker files and headers in the archive: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para> Make a bean archive a bean bundle by adding special OSGi marker headers in its
                     <code>META-INF/Manifest.MF</code> file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para> Or, in the other way, make a bundle a bean bundle by adding a <code>META-INF/bean.xml</code>
                  file.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist></para>
      <para>Thus a bean bundle has both <code>META-INF/bean.xml</code> file
         and OSGi marker headers in its <code>META-INF/Manifest.MF</code> file.</para>
      <para>However there is a few other information that Weld-OSGi might need in order to perform a correct extension.
         In particular a bean bundle can not be manage by the extension bundle but by his own embedded CDI container.
         For that there is a new manifest header.</para>
      <section>
         <title>The <code>META-INF/bean.xml</code> file </title>
         <para>The beans.xml file follows no particular rules and should be the same as in a native CDI environment.
            Thus it can be completely empty or declare interceptors, decorators or alternatives as a regular CDI
            beans.xml file.</para>
         <para>There will be no different behavior with a classic bean archive except for Weld-OSGi extension new
            utilities. But these don't need any modification on the <code>META-INF/bean.xml</code> file.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
         <title>The Embedded-CDIContainer <code>META-INF/Manifest.MF</code> header </title>
         <para>This header prevents the extension bundle to automatically manage the bean bundle that set this manifest
            header to true. So the bean bundle can be manage more finely by the user or use a different CDI container.
            If this header is set to false or is not present in the <code>META-INF/Manifest.MF</code> file then the bean
            bundle will be automatically manage by the extension bundle (if it is started).</para>
      </section>
   </chapter>
   
<!--
   vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</part>