<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<preface>
   <title>Preface</title>
   
   <section>
      <title>About naming and references</title>
      
      <section>
         <title>References</title>
         
         <para>
            This document uses both CDI and OSGi specification documentations as technical references. You may
            refer to these documents for a better understanding of CDI and OSGi functionality, references and naming
            conventions. Weld-OSGi comes with other documentations and you may refer to API JavaDoc and user manual for
            a better understanding of Weld-OSGi.
         </para>       
      </section>
      
      <section>
         <title>Bundle types</title>
         <para>This document discners differents bundle types for OSGi environment using Weld-OSGi: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para><emphasis>Bundle</emphasis> reffers to any bundle deployable in the OSGi environment as a Java
                  archive containing OSGi marker headers in its <code>META-INF/Manifest.MF</code> file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para><emphasis>Bean bundle</emphasis> reffers to any bundle deployable in the OSGi environment and
                  managable by Weld-OSGi as a <emphasis>bundle</emphasis> containing CDI marker file
                  <code>META-INF/bean.xml</code>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para><emphasis>Regular bundle</emphasis> reffers to any bundle deployable in the OSGi environment and
                  not managable by Weld-OSGi as a <emphasis>bundle</emphasis> not containing CDI marker file.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist></para>         
      </section>
   </section>
   
   <section>
      <title>What is this specification for ?</title>
      
      <section>
         <title>Contracts</title>
         
         <para>This specification defines: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>The architecture, organization and workflow of the Weld-OSGi framework.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>The programming model for, and responsabilities of, application developper who uses the
                  Weld-OSGi framework.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>The programming model for, and responsabilities of, vendor who provides the compatibility of
                  another CDI implementation.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist></para>
         <para>TODO table of content presentation</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
         <title>What is Weld-OSGi ?</title>
         
         <para>Weld-OSGi is an extension to the Weld project as a framework for developping applications in OSGi
            environment. Weld-OSGi aims at: <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Providing a support for OSGi environments to the Weld project.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Adressing the OSGi complexity using the CDI programming model.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
         <para>Weld-OSGi is a group of four bundles deployable in any OSGi environment. It allows the usage of bean
            bundles in these OSGi environments.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section>
         <title>Third party dependencies and environment</title>
         
         <para>Weld-OSGi may run into an OSGi environment, therefore it requires an OSGi implementation framework to
            run in (such as Apache Felix, Equinox, Knopflerfish ...).</para>
         <para>Weld-OSGi logs its operations using the SLF4J logging facade and the LogBack logging
            implementation.</para>
         <para>Weld-OSGi is a part of the Weld project and may use any of the Weld project dependencies.</para>
      </section>
   </section>
   
<!--
   vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</preface>