<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<chapter id="producermethods">
 
   <title>Producer methods</title>
  
   <para>
      Producer methods let us overcome certain limitations that arise when a container, instead of the application, is
      responsible for instantiating objects. They're also the easiest way to integrate objects which are not beans into
      the CDI environment. <!--(We'll meet a second approach in <xref linkend="xml"/>, a chapter covering the Weld XML
      extension).-->
   </para>

   <para>According to the spec:</para>

   <blockquote>

      <para>A producer method acts as a source of objects to be injected, where:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>the objects to be injected are not required to be instances of beans,</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>the concrete type of the objects to be injected may vary at runtime or</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               the objects require some custom initialization that is not performed by the bean constructor
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </blockquote>

   <para>For example, producer methods let us:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>expose a JPA entity as a bean,</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>expose any JDK class as a bean,</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               define multiple beans, with different scopes or initialization, for the same implementation class, or
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>vary the implementation of a bean type at runtime.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         In particular, producer methods let us use runtime polymorphism with CDI. As we've seen, alternative beans are
         one solution to the problem of deployment-time polymorphism. But once the system is deployed, the CDI
         implementation is fixed. A producer method has no such limitation:
      </para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@SessionScoped
public class Preferences {
   private PaymentStrategyType paymentStrategy;
   ...
   @Produces @Preferred 
   public PaymentStrategy getPaymentStrategy() {
       switch (paymentStrategy) {
           case CREDIT_CARD: return new CreditCardPaymentStrategy();
           case CHECK: return new CheckPaymentStrategy();
           case PAYPAL: return new PayPalPaymentStrategy();
           default: return null;
       } 
   }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>Consider an injection point:</para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Preferred PaymentStrategy paymentStrategy;]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         This injection point has the same type and qualifier annotations as the producer method, so it resolves to the
         producer method using the usual CDI injection rules. The producer method will be called by the container to
         obtain an instance to service this injection point.
      </para>

      <section>
         <title>Scope of a producer method</title>

         <para>
            The scope of the producer method defaults to <literal>@Dependent</literal>, and so it will be called
            <emphasis>every time</emphasis> the container injects this field or any other field that resolves to the
            same producer method. Thus, there could be multiple instances of the <literal>PaymentStrategy</literal>
            object for each user session.
         </para>

         <para>
            To change this behavior, we can add a <literal>@SessionScoped</literal> annotation to the method.
         </para>
  
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Produces @Preferred @SessionScoped
public PaymentStrategy getPaymentStrategy() {
   ...
}]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            Now, when the producer method is called, the returned <literal>PaymentStrategy</literal> will be bound to
            the session context. The producer method won't be called again in the same session.
         </para>
  
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Injection into producer methods</title>

         <para>
            There's one potential problem with the code above. The implementations of
            <literal>CreditCardPaymentStrategy</literal> are instantiated using the Java <literal>new</literal>
            operator. Objects instantiated directly by the application can't take advantage of dependency injection and
            don't have interceptors.
         </para>
   
         <para>
            If this isn't what we want we can use dependency injection into the producer method to obtain bean
            instances:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Produces @Preferred @SessionScoped
public PaymentStrategy getPaymentStrategy(CreditCardPaymentStrategy ccps,
                                          CheckPaymentStrategy cps,
                                          PayPalPaymentStrategy ppps) {
   switch (paymentStrategy) {
      case CREDIT_CARD: return ccps;
      case CHEQUE: return cps;
      case PAYPAL: return ppps;
      default: return null;
   } 
}]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            Wait, what if <literal>CreditCardPaymentStrategy</literal> is a request-scoped bean? Then the producer
            method has the effect of "promoting" the current request scoped instance into session scope. This is almost
            certainly a bug! The request scoped object will be destroyed by the container before the session ends, but
            the reference to the object will be left "hanging" in the session scope. This error will
            <emphasis>not</emphasis> be detected by the container, so please take extra care when returning bean
            instances from producer methods!
         </para>
  
         <para>
            There's at least three ways we could go about fixing this bug. We could change the scope of the
            <literal>CreditCardPaymentStrategy</literal> implementation, but this would affect other clients of that
            bean.  A better option would be to change the scope of the producer method to <literal>@Dependent</literal>
            or <literal>@RequestScoped</literal>.
         </para>
  
         <para>But a more common solution is to use the special <literal>@New</literal> qualifier annotation.</para>
  
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Use of <literal>@New</literal> with producer methods</title>
  
         <para>Consider the following producer method:</para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Produces @Preferred @SessionScoped
public PaymentStrategy getPaymentStrategy(@New CreditCardPaymentStrategy ccps,
                                          @New CheckPaymentStrategy cps,
                                          @New PayPalPaymentStrategy ppps) {
   switch (paymentStrategy) {
      case CREDIT_CARD: return ccps;
      case CHEQUE: return cps;
      case PAYPAL: return ppps;
      default: return null;
   } 
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Then a new <emphasis>dependent</emphasis> instance of <literal>CreditCardPaymentStrategy</literal> will be
         created, passed to the producer method, returned by the producer method and finally bound to the session
         context. The dependent object won't be destroyed until the <literal>Preferences</literal> object is destroyed,
         at the end of the session.
      </para>

   </section>

<!--
vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</chapter>
