<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<chapter id="beanscdi">
   <title>More about beans</title>
  
      <para>
         A bean is usually an application class that contains business logic. It can be called directly from Java code,
         or it can be invoked via the Unified EL. A bean can access transactional resources. Dependencies between beans
         are managed automatically by the container. Most beans are <emphasis>stateful</emphasis> and
         <emphasis>contextual</emphasis>. The lifecycle of a bean is always managed by the container.
      </para>

      <para>
         Let's back up a second. What does it really mean to be <emphasis>contextual</emphasis>? Since beans can be
         stateful, it matters <emphasis>which</emphasis> bean instance I have. Unlike a stateless component model (for
         example, stateless session beans) or a singleton component model (such as servlets, or singleton beans),
         different clients of a bean see the bean in different states. The client-visible state depends upon which
         instance of the bean the client has a reference to.
      </para> 

      <para>
         However, like a stateless or singleton model, but <emphasis>unlike</emphasis> stateful session beans, the
         client does not control the lifecycle of the instance by explicitly creating and destroying it. Instead, the
         <emphasis>scope</emphasis> of the bean determines:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>the lifecycle of each instance of the bean and</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>which clients share a reference to a particular instance of the bean.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  
      <para>
         For a given thread in a CDI application, there can be an <emphasis>active context</emphasis> associated with
         the scope of the bean. This context may be unique to the thread (for example, if the bean is request scoped),
         or it may be shared with certain other threads (for example, if the bean is session scoped) or even all other
         threads (if it is application scoped).
      </para>

      <para>
         Clients (for example, other beans) executing in the same context will see the same instance of the bean. But
         clients in a different context may see a different instance (depending on the relationship between the
         contexts).
      </para>

      <para>
         One great advantage of the contextual model is that it allows stateful beans to be treated like services! The
         client need not concern itself with managing the lifecycle of the bean it's using, <emphasis>nor does it even
         need to know what that lifecycle is.</emphasis> Beans interact by passing messages, and the bean implementations
         define the lifecycle of their own state. The beans are loosely coupled because:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>they interact via well-defined public APIs, and</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>their lifecycles are completely decoupled.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         We can replace one bean with a different bean that implements the same interface and has a different lifecycle
         (a different scope) without affecting the first bean implementation. See <xref linkend="alternatives"/> for
         information about overriding bean implementations at deployment time.
      </para>
  
      <para>
         Not all clients of a bean are beans themselves. Other objects such as servlets or message-driven beans &mdash; 
         which are by nature not injectable, contextual objects &mdash; can also obtain references to beans by
         injection.
      </para>

   <section id="bean-anatomy">
      <title>The anatomy of a bean</title>
  
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
      <para>Enough hand-waving. According to the specification, the anatomy of a bean is:</para>
=======
      <para>According to the specification, a bean comprises the following attributes:</para>
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
      <para>Enough hand-waving. According to the specification, the anatomy of a bean is:</para>
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.

      <blockquote>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>A (nonempty) set of bean types</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>A (nonempty) set of qualifiers</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>A scope</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Optionally, a bean EL name</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>A set of interceptor bindings</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>A bean implementation</para></listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         
         <para>Furthermore, a bean may or may not be an alternative.</para>

      </blockquote>

      <para>Let's see what all this new terminology means.</para>

      <section>
         <title>Bean types, qualifiers and dependency injection</title>

         <para>
            Beans usually acquire references to other beans via dependency injection. Any injected attribute specifies a
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            "contract" that must be satisfied by the bean to be injected. The contract specified includes:
=======
            "contract" that must be satisfied by the bean to be injected. The contract defines:
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            "contract" that must be satisfied by the bean to be injected. The contract specified includes:
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>a bean type, together with</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>a set of qualifiers.</para></listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            A bean type is a user-defined class or interface; a type that is client-visible. If the bean is an EJB
            session bean, the bean type is the <literal>@Local</literal> interface or bean-class local view. A bean 
            may have multiple bean types. For example, the following bean has four bean types:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class BookShop 
      extends Business 
      implements Shop<Book> {
   ...
}]]></programlisting> 

         <para>  
            The bean types are <literal>BookShop</literal>, <literal>Business</literal> and
            <literal>Shop&lt;Book&gt;</literal>, as well as the implicit type <literal>java.lang.Object</literal>.
            (Notice that a parameterized type is a legal bean type). 
         </para>
         
         <para>
            Meanwhile, this session bean has only the local interfaces <literal>BookShop</literal>, 
            <literal>Auditable</literal> and <literal>java.lang.Object</literal> as bean types, since the bean class, 
            <literal>BookShopBean</literal> is not a client-visible type.
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Stateful
public class BookShopBean 
      extends Business 
      implements BookShop, Auditable {
   ...
}]]></programlisting> 

         <note>
            <para>
               The bean types of a session bean include local interfaces and the bean class local view (if any). 
               EJB remote interfaces are not considered bean types of a session bean. You can't inject an EJB using
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
               its remote interface unless you define a <emphasis>resource</emphasis>. If you want to know more,
               skip ahead to <xref linkend="resources"/>.
=======
               its remote interface unless you define a <emphasis>resource</emphasis> &mdash; see <xref linkend="resources"/>
               for details.
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
               its remote interface unless you define a <emphasis>resource</emphasis>. If you want to know more,
               skip ahead to <xref linkend="resources"/>.
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
            </para>
         </note>

         <para>
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            To restrict the bean types to an explicit set, annotate the bean with the <literal>@Typed</literal>
=======
            Restrict the bean types to an explicit set by annotating the bean with the <literal>@Typed</literal>
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            To restrict the bean types to an explicit set, annotate the bean with the <literal>@Typed</literal>
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
            annotation and listing the classes that should be types. The bean types of the following bean have been
            restricted to <literal>Shop&lt;Book&gt;</literal>, together with <literal>java.lang.Object</literal>:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Typed(Shop.class)
public class BookShop 
      extends Business 
      implements Shop<Book> {
   ...
}]]></programlisting> 

         <para>
            Sometimes, a bean type alone does not provide enough information for the container to know which bean to inject.
            For instance, suppose we have two implementations of the <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal> interface:
            <literal>CreditCardPaymentProcessor</literal> and <literal>DebitPaymentProcessor</literal>. Injecting a field of 
            type <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal> introduces an ambiguous condition. In these cases, the client must 
            specify some additional quality of the implementation it is interested in. We model this kind of "quality" using
            a qualifier.
         </para>

         <para>
            A qualifier is a user-defined annotation that is itself annotated <literal>@Qualifer</literal>. A qualifier 
            annotation is an extension of the type system. It lets us disambiguate a type without having to fall back to 
            string-based names. Here's an example of a qualifier annotation:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Qualifier
@Target({TYPE, METHOD, PARAMETER, FIELD})
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface CreditCard {}]]></programlisting> 

         <para>
            You may not be used to seeing the definition of an annotation. In fact, this might be the first time you've
            encountered one. With CDI, annotation definitions will become a familiar artifact as you'll be creating them 
            from time to time. 
         </para>
         
         <note>
            <para>
               Pay attention to the names of the built-in annotations in CDI and EJB. You will notice that they are 
               often adjectives. We encourage you to follow this convention when creating your custom annotations, 
               since they serve to describe the behaviors and roles of the class.
            </para>
         </note>
            
         <para>
            Now that we have defined a qualifier annotation, we can use it to disambiguate an injection point. The 
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
=======
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
            following injection point has the bean type <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal> and the qualifier
            <literal>@CreditCard</literal>:
=======
            following injection point has the <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal> bean type and the 
            <literal>@CreditCard</literal> qualifier annotation:
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @CreditCard PaymentProcessor paymentProcessor]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            For each injection point, the container searches for a bean which satisfies the contract, one which has
            the bean type and all the qualifiers. If it finds exactly one matching bean, it injects an instance of 
            that bean. If it doesn't, it reports an error to the user.
         </para>
         
         <para>
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            We can also specify the qualifiers of a bean by annotating the bean class. The following bean has the
            qualifier <literal>@CreditCard</literal> and implements the bean type <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal>.
=======
            To specify the qualifiers of a bean, annotate the bean class. The following bean has the
            <literal>@CreditCard</literal> qualifier and implements the <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal> bean type. 
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            We can also specify the qualifiers of a bean by annotating the bean class. The following bean has the
            qualifier <literal>@CreditCard</literal> and implements the bean type <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal>.
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
            Therefore, it satisfies our qualified injection point:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@CreditCard
public class CreditCardPaymentProcessor 
    implements PaymentProcessor { ... }]]></programlisting>

         <note>
            <para>
               If a bean or an injection point does not explicitly specify a qualifier, it has the default qualifier,
               <literal>@Default</literal>.
            </para>
         </note>
         
         <!-- 
         <note>
            <para>
               All beans have the qualifier, <literal>@Any</literal>.
            </para>
         </note>
         -->
         
         <para>
            CDI also defines a simple <emphasis>resolution rule</emphasis> that helps the container decide what 
            to do if there is more than one bean that satisfies a particular contract. 
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            We cover this in more detail in <xref linkend="injection"/>.
=======
            See <xref linkend="injection"/> for details.
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            We cover this in more detail in <xref linkend="injection"/>.
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
         </para>
         
         <!--
         <note>
            <para>
               If you're expecting more than one bean to satisfy the contract, you can inject an <literal>Instance</literal>,
               object which let's you iterate over all the beans which satisfy the contract. For example, we can iterate
               over all our implementations of <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal> using:
            </para>
            <programlisting role="JAVA">@Inject void init(@Any Instance&lt;PaymentProcessor&gt; paymentProcessorInstance) {
    for (PaymentProcessor pp: paymentProcessorInstance) { ... }
}</programlisting>
         </note>
         -->
           
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Scope</title>
         <!-- I wonder whether the explanation of contextual above would fit better here -->

         <para>
            The <emphasis>scope</emphasis> of a bean defines the lifecycle and visibility of its instances.
            The CDI context model is extensible, accommodating arbitrary scopes. However, certain important scopes are
            built into the specification, and provided by the container. Each scope is represented by an annotation
            type.
         </para>

         <para>
            For example, any web application may have <emphasis>session scoped</emphasis> bean:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public @SessionScoped
class ShoppingCart implements Serializable { ... }]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            An instance of a session-scoped bean is bound to a user session
            and is shared by all requests that execute in the context of that session.
         </para>

         <note>
            <para>
               Keep in mind that once a bean is bound to a context, it remains in that context until the context is
               destroyed. There is no way to manually remove a bean from a context. If you don't want the bean to sit 
               in the session indefinitely, consider using another scope with a shorter lifespan, such as the request 
               or conversation scope.
            </para>
         </note>

         <para>
            If a scope is not explicitly specified, then the bean belongs to a special scope called the
            <emphasis>dependent pseudo-scope</emphasis>. Beans with this scope live to serve the object into which they
            were injected, which means their lifecycle is bound to the lifecycle of that object.
         </para>

<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
         <para>We cover scopes in more detail in <xref linkend="scopescontexts"/>.</para>
=======
         <para>Scopes are covered in further detail in <xref linkend="scopescontexts"/>.</para>
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
         <para>We cover scopes in more detail in <xref linkend="scopescontexts"/>.</para>
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.

      </section>

      <section>
         <title>EL name</title>

         <para>
            To reference a bean in non-Java code that supports Unified Expression Language (EL) expressions, for example, 
            in a JSP or JSF page, you must assign the bean an <emphasis>EL name</emphasis>.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            The EL name is specified using the <literal>@Named</literal> annotation, as shown here:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public @SessionScoped @Named("cart")
class ShoppingCart implements Serializable { ... }]]></programlisting>

         <para>Now we can easily use the bean in any JSF or JSP page:</para>

         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<h:dataTable value="#{cart.lineItems}" var="item">
   ...
</h:dataTable>]]></programlisting>

         <note>
            <para>
               The <literal>@Named</literal> annotation is not what makes the class a bean. Most classes in a bean
               archive are already recognized as beans. The <literal>@Named</literal> annotation just makes it
               possible to reference the bean from the EL, most commonly from a JSF view.
            </para>
         </note>

         <para>
            We can let CDI choose a name for us by leaving off the value of the <literal>@Named</literal> annotation:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public @SessionScoped @Named
class ShoppingCart implements Serializable { ... }]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            The name defaults to the unqualified class name, decapitalized; in this case,
            <literal>shoppingCart</literal>.
         </para>

      </section>

      <!-- TODO the alternative section needs to be spruced up to support the text that comes in subsequent chapters. 
      The reader needs to feel confident than they would know how to create an alternative and enable it. -->
      <section>
         <title>Alternatives</title>

         <para>
            We've already seen how qualifiers let us choose between multiple implementations of an interface 
            at development time. But sometimes we have an interface (or other bean type) whose implementation 
            varies depending upon the deployment environment. For example, we may want to use a mock 
            implementation in a testing environment. An <emphasis>alternative</emphasis> may be declared by 
            annotating the bean class with the <literal>@Alternative</literal> annotation.
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public @Alternative
class MockPaymentProcessor extends PaymentProcessorImpl { ... }]]></programlisting> 
         
         <para>
            We normally annotate a bean <literal>@Alternative</literal> only when there is some other
            implementation of an interface it implements (or of any of its bean types). We can choose between 
            alternatives at deployment time by <emphasis>selecting</emphasis> an alternative in the CDI 
            deployment descriptor <literal>META-INF/beans.xml</literal> of the JAR or Java EE module that uses 
            it. Different modules can specify that they use different alternatives.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            We cover alternatives in more detail in <xref linkend="alternatives"/>.
         </para>
         
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Interceptor binding types</title>

         <para>
            You might be familiar with the use of interceptors in EJB 3.0. In Java EE 6, this functionality has
            been generalized to work with other managed beans. That's right, you no longer have to make your bean 
            an EJB just to intercept its methods.
         </para>

         <para>
            The way that interceptors were defined in Java EE 5 was counter-intuitive. You were required to specify the
            <emphasis>implementation</emphasis> of the interceptor directly on the <emphasis>implementation</emphasis>
            of the EJB, either in the <literal>@Interceptors</literal> annotation or in the XML descriptor. You might as
            well just put the interceptor code <emphasis>in</emphasis> the implementation! Additionally, the order in which
            the interceptors were applied was taken from the order in which they were declared in the annotation or the XML
            descriptor. This was not so bad if the interceptors were applied to a single bean, but when applied repeatedly
            there was a possibility of inadvertently defining a different order for different beans. Now that's a problem.
         </para>

         <para>
            CDI provides a new approach to binding interceptors to beans that introduces a level of indirection (and
            thus control). We must define an <emphasis>interceptor binding type</emphasis> to describe the behavior 
            implemented by the interceptor.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            An interceptor binding type is a user-defined annotation that is itself annotated <literal>@InterceptorBinding</literal>.
            It lets us bind interceptor classes to bean classes with no direct dependency between the two classes. The following
            code defines the <literal>Transactional</literal> interceptor binding type:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@InterceptorBinding
@Inherited
@Target( { TYPE, METHOD })
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface Transactional {}]]></programlisting>

         <para>
           The interceptor that implements transaction management declares this annotation: 
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public @Transactional @Interceptor
class TransactionInterceptor { ... }]]></programlisting>
         
         <para>
            We can apply the interceptor to a bean by annotating the bean class with the same interceptor binding type:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public @SessionScoped @Transactional
class ShoppingCart implements Serializable { ... }]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            Notice that <literal>ShoppingCart</literal> and <literal>TransactionInterceptor</literal> don't know 
            anything about each other.
         </para>

         <para>
            Interceptors are deployment-specific &mdash; a <literal>TransactionInterceptor</literal> is unnecessary in a
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            unit test. By default, an interceptor is disabled. You can enable interceptors in the CDI deployment 
=======
            unit test. By default, an interceptor is disabled. Enable interceptors in the CDI deployment 
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            unit test. By default, an interceptor is disabled. You can enable interceptors in the CDI deployment 
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
            descriptor file (<literal>META-INF/beans.xml</literal>) of the JAR or Java EE module. This is also where we
            specify the interceptor ordering.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            For more information about interceptors and decorators, see <xref linkend="interceptors"/> and <xref
            linkend="decorators"/> respectively.
         </para>

      </section>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>What kinds of classes are beans?</title>
     
      <para>
         We've already seen two types of beans: JavaBeans and EJB session beans. CDI implementations support several other
         bean types out-of-the-box.
      </para>
     
      <section>
         <title>Managed beans</title>

         <para>
            A managed bean is a Java class. The basic lifecycle and semantics of a managed bean are defined by the 
            Managed Beans specification. You can explicitly declare a managed bean by annotating the bean class
            <literal>@ManagedBean</literal>, but in CDI you don't need to. According to the specification, the CDI 
            container treats any class that satisfies the following conditions as a managed bean:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>It is not a non-static inner class.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>It is a concrete class, or is annotated <literal>@Decorator</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  It is not annotated with an EJB component-defining annotation or declared as an EJB bean class in
                  <literal>ejb-jar.xml</literal>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>It does not implement <literal>javax.enterprise.inject.spi.Extension</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  It has an appropriate constructor &mdash; either:
               </para>
               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>the class has a constructor with no parameters, or</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>the class declares a constructor annotated <literal>@Inject</literal>.</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <note>
           <para>
             According to this definition, JPA entities are technically managed beans. However, entities have their own 
             special lifecycle, state and identity model and are usually instantiated by JPA or using <literal>new</literal>. 
             Therefore we don't recommend directly injecting an entity class. We especially recommend against assigning
             a scope other than <literal>@Dependent</literal> to an entity class, since JPA is not able to persist 
             injected CDI proxies.
           </para>
         </note>

         <para>The unrestricted set of bean types for a managed bean contains the bean class, every superclass, and all 
         interfaces it implements directly or indirectly.</para>

         <para>If a managed bean has a public field, it must have the default scope <literal>@Dependent</literal>.</para>
         
         <para>Managed beans support the <literal>@PostConstruct</literal> and <literal>@PreDestroy</literal> lifecycle
         callbacks.</para>
         
         <para>
            Session beans are also, technically, managed beans. However, since they have their own special lifecycle and 
            take advantage of additional enterprise services, the CDI specification considers them to be a different
            kind of bean.
         </para>
         
      </section>
     
      <section>
         <title>Session beans</title>

         <para>
            Session beans belong to the EJB specification. They have a special lifecycle, state management and concurrency
            model that is different to other managed beans and non-managed Java objects. But session beans participate in 
            CDI just like any other bean. You can inject one session bean into another session bean, a managed bean into a 
            session bean, a session bean into a managed bean, have a managed bean observe an event raised by a session bean, 
            and so on.
         </para>

         <note>
            <para>
               Message-driven and entity beans are by nature non-contextual objects and may not be injected into other
               objects. However, message-driven beans can take advantage of some CDI functionality, such as dependency 
               injection, interceptors, and decorators. In fact, CDI will perform injection into any session or 
               message-driven bean, even those which are not contextual instances.
            </para>
         </note>

         <para>
            The unrestricted set of bean types for a session bean contains all local interfaces of the bean and their
            superinterfaces. If the session bean has a bean class local view, the unrestricted set of bean types
            contains the bean class and all superclasses. In addition, <literal>java.lang.Object</literal> is a bean
            type of every session bean. However, remote interfaces are <emphasis>not</emphasis> included in the set of bean
            types.
         </para>

         <para>There's no reason to explicitly declare the scope of a stateless session bean or singleton session bean. 
         The EJB container controls the lifecycle of these beans, according to the semantics of the <literal>@Stateless</literal>
         or <literal>@Singleton</literal> declaration. On the other hand, a stateful session bean may have any scope.</para>
         
         <para>
            Stateful session beans may define a <emphasis>remove method</emphasis>, annotated <literal>@Remove</literal>, 
            that is used by the application to indicate that an instance should be destroyed. However, for a contextual 
            instance of the bean &mdash; an instance under the control of CDI &mdash; this method may only be called by the 
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            application if the bean has <literal>@Dependent</literal> scope. For beans with other scopes, the application 
=======
            application if the bean has the <literal>@Dependent</literal> scope. For beans with other scopes, the application 
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            application if the bean has <literal>@Dependent</literal> scope. For beans with other scopes, the application 
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
            must let the container destroy the bean.
         </para>

         <para>
            So, when should we use a session bean instead of a plain managed bean? Whenever we need the advanced enterprise
            services offered by EJB, such as:
         </para>
       
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>method-level transaction management and security,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>concurrency management,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>instance-level passivation for stateful session beans and 
              instance-pooling for stateless session beans,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>remote or web service invocation, or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>timers and asynchronous methods.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       
         <para>When we don't need any of these things, an ordinary managed bean will serve just fine.</para>
       
         <para>
            Many beans (including any <literal>@SessionScoped</literal> or <literal>@ApplicationScoped</literal> 
            beans) are available for concurrent access. Therefore, the concurrency management provided by EJB 3.1 
            is especially useful. Most session and application scoped beans should be EJBs.
         </para>
       
         <para>
            Beans that hold references to heavy-weight resources, or hold a lot of internal state, benefit from the
            advanced container-managed lifecycle defined by the EJB stateless/stateful/singleton model, with its
            support for passivation and instance pooling.
         </para>
       
         <para>
            Finally, it's usually obvious when method-level transaction management, method-level security, timers,
            remote methods or asynchronous methods are needed.
         </para>

         <para>
            The point we're trying to make is: use a session bean when you need the services it provides, not just 
            because you want to use dependency injection, lifecycle management, or interceptors. Java EE 6 provides
            a graduated programming model. It's usually easy to start with an ordinary managed bean, and later turn 
            it into an EJB just by adding one of the following annotations: <literal>@Stateless</literal>, 
            <literal>@Stateful</literal> or <literal>@Singleton</literal>.
         </para>
         
     </section>
     
      <section>
         <title>Producer methods</title>
   
         <para>
            Not everything that needs to be injected can be boiled down to a bean class instantiated by the container
            using <literal>new</literal>. There are plenty of cases where we need additional control. What if we need 
            to decide at runtime which implementation of a type to instantiate and inject? What if we need to inject  
            an object that is obtained by querying a service or transactional resource, for example, by executing a JPA 
            query?
         </para>

         <para>
            A <emphasis>producer method</emphasis> is a method that acts as a source of bean instances. The method 
            declaration itself describes the bean and the container invokes the method to obtain an instance of the 
            bean when no instance exists in the specified context. A producer method lets the application take full 
            control of the bean instantiation process.
         </para>
            
         <para>
            A producer method is declared by annotating a method of a bean class with the <literal>@Produces</literal> 
            annotation.
         </para>
   
   <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@ApplicationScoped
public class RandomNumberGenerator {
   
   private Random random = new Random(System.currentTimeMillis());
       
   @Produces @Named @Random int getRandomNumber() {
      return random.nextInt(100);
   }
   
}]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            We can't write a bean class that is itself a random number, but we can write a method that returns 
            a random number. By making this method a producer method, we allow the return value of the method (in this 
            case, an <literal>Integer</literal>) to be injected. We can even specify a qualifier (in this instance, 
            <literal>@Random</literal>, a scope) and an EL name (which in this case defaults to <literal>randomNumber</literal>
            according to the JavaBeans property name convention). Now we can get a random number anywhere:
         </para>
   
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Random int randomNumber;]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            Even in a Unified EL expression:
         </para>

         <programlisting><![CDATA[<p>Your raffle number is #{randomNumber}.</p>]]></programlisting> 
         
         <para>
            A producer method must be a non-abstract method of a managed bean class or session bean class. A producer
            method can be either static or non-static. If the bean is a session bean, the producer method must be either
            a business method of the EJB or a static method of the bean class.
         </para>

         <para>
            The bean types of a producer method depend upon the method return type:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  If the return type is an interface, the unrestricted set of bean types contains the return type, all
                  interfaces it extends directly or indirectly, and <literal>java.lang.Object</literal>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  If a return type is primitive or is a Java array type, the unrestricted set of bean types contains
                  exactly two types: the method return type and <literal>java.lang.Object</literal>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  If the return type is a class, the unrestricted set of bean types contains the return type, every
                  superclass, and all interfaces it implements directly or indirectly.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <note>
            <para>
               Producer methods and fields can have a primitive bean type. For the purpose of resolving dependencies,
               primitive types are considered to be identical to their corresponding wrapper types in 
               <literal>java.lang</literal>.
            </para>
         </note>

         <para>
            If the producer method has method parameters, the container looks for a bean that satisfies the type
            and qualifiers of each parameter and passes it to the method automatically &mdash; another form of 
            dependency injection.
         </para>
   
   <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Produces Set<Roles> getRoles(User user) {
   return user.getRoles();
}]]></programlisting>
   
         <para>We cover producer methods in more detail in <xref linkend="producermethods"/>.</para>
   
     </section>

      <section>
         <title>Producer fields</title>

         <para>
            A <emphasis>producer field</emphasis> is a simpler alternative to a producer method. A producer field is 
            declared by annotating a field of a bean class with the <literal>@Produces</literal> annotation &mdash; the 
            same annotation used for producer methods.
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class Shop {
   @Produces PaymentProcessor paymentProcessor = ....;
   @Produces @Catalog List<Product> products = ....;
}]]></programlisting>
         
         <para>
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            The rules for determining the bean types of a producer field correspond to the rules for 
            producer methods.
=======
            The rules for determining the bean types of a producer field are identical to those of determining the bean 
            types of a producer method.
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            The rules for determining the bean types of a producer field correspond to the rules for 
            producer methods.
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
         </para>

         <para>
            A producer field can be used as a shortcut to avoid writing a useless getter method. 
<<<<<<< HEAD
<<<<<<< HEAD
            Producer fields also serve a specific purpose as adaptors for Java EE component 
=======
            However, producer fields serve a specific purpose as adaptors for Java EE component 
>>>>>>> b63c52c6e5f95bb1a6e0263ce462eb67ed0790ef
=======
            Producer fields also serve a specific purpose as adaptors for Java EE component 
>>>>>>> 14b5c34... Spelling and grammar changes, and minor paragraph rewrites for clarity.
            environment injection. See <xref linkend="resources"/> for more details.
         </para>

      </section>
   
   </section>
   
   <!--
   
   <section id="bean-descriptor">
      <title>The (minimal) bean descriptor</title>

      <para>
         First, it's important to understand that the XML bean descriptor in CDI (beans.xml) is not there to define
         beans in XML, like in other popular bean containers. Rather, you use this file to enable CDI services for the
         current bean archive that is difficult to define consistently in Java or which you don't want to define in Java
         (e.g. to accommodate testing).
      </para>
      
      <para>
         For example, the XML is used to enable interceptors (which are disabled by default) and define interceptor
         ordering. So the bean descriptor <emphasis>complements</emphasis> the metadata that is provided in the Java
         language syntax. (You may still want to define beans in XML for other reasons, but that is the concern of an
         extension).
      </para>

      <para>
         Let's first ask why the beans.xml is required, then look at what services it is used used to enable.
      </para>

      <section>
         <title>Why is beans.xml required?</title>

         <para>
            You may be wondering, if beans are not described using XML, why do we need beans.xml at all, particularly if
            you don't have anything that you would need the bean descriptor to enable (alternatives, interceptors or
            decorators)?
         </para>

         <para>
            There are two things about CDI that we need to keep in mind:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  CDI does not require any special declaration for a Java class to be injected - that's right, no
                  annotation or XML declaration at all!
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  CDI does not define any special kind of module - CDI beans can be deployed in a library jar, EJB jar,
                  war, rar, or JVM classpath directory.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            The CDI specification calls the process of identifying beans in modules <emphasis>bean discovery</emphasis>.
         </para>

         <para>
            So there are potentially a lot of classes in the classpath which might be beans! We don't want to force the
            container to scan every one of those classes at startup and build its internal metamodel for each of them. This
            really could make bean discovery very slow.
         </para>

         <para>
            But there's another reason we need to give the user some control over which classes are available for
            injection. We don't want every class in the classpath to potentially match an injection point, including
            classes that were never intended to be injected into things. This would force the developer to have to use
            qualifiers much more often to disambiguate injection points.
         </para>

         <para>
            So we have two choices. We could have the developer:
         </para>

         <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>explicitly exclude modules which do not contain beans, or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>explicitly declare modules which do contain beans.</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>

         <para>
            It should be clear that the second option is a much better way to go. Thus, CDI has the notion of a bean
            archive. A bean archive is just a module that has a file named beans.xml in the META-INF directory. The
            container looks for beans in bean archives. It ignores other modules.
         </para>

         <para>
            Now, you might be wondering if we've got the granularity wrong here. Why should module be the right criteria to
            use for including/excluding a class. Why not consider:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>a class-level annotation,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>the package,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>some type it implements or extends, or</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>some naming convention.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            We've got the first option covered. Annotate a bean <literal>@Alternative</literal>, or with an alternative
            stereotype, and it will be considered disabled by CDI, as long as you don't explicitly enable it in
            beans.xml. That's not quite the same thing as excluding the class from scanning altogether, but it's close.
            (One difference is that a portable extension with still get a <literal>ProcessAnnotatedType</literal> event
            for that class).
         </para>

         <para>
            A future version of CDI might allow you to declare excluded packages in beans.xml. Excluding a bean by type or
            naming convention isn't really that appealing. In the world of CDI, we use stereotypes for identifying
            architectural roles. We don't use marker interfaces or naming conventions. Names really shouldn't affect
            functionality as it is too fragile.
         </para>

         <para>
            Enough theory, what elements are available in beans.xml?
         </para>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Bean descriptor schema</title>

         <para>
            If you don't need to activate any interceptors, decorators or alternatives (you just have plain beans that
            you need to use in an archive), the beans.xml file can be <emphasis>empty</emphasis>. If you do have one
            of these requirements, then you need to start popularing the descriptor.
         </para>

         <para>
            The root element of a beans.xml file is <literal>beans</literal>, with the following <ulink
            url="http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/weld/api/trunk/cdi/src/main/resources/beans.xsd">schema</ulink>:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="
      http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee 
      http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee/beans_1_0.xsd">
</beans>]]></programlisting> 

         <para>
            The <literal>beans</literal> element can have one or more of each of the following children: 
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para><literal>interceptors</literal></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para><literal>decorators</literal></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para><literal>alternatives</literal></para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            Let's look at each element in detail.
         </para>

         <section>
            <title>&lt;interceptors&gt;</title>

            <para>
               By default, a bean archive has no enabled interceptors bound via interceptor bindings. An interceptor
               must be explicitly enabled by listing the fully qualified class name in a child &lt;class&gt; element of
               &lt;interceptors&gt;.
            </para>
            
            <para>
               There may be zero or more interceptor class elements. The order of the class
               declarations determines the interceptor ordering. Interceptors which occur earlier in the list are called
               first. The same class may not be listed twice. And of course, the class must exist and it must be an
               interceptor class.
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<interceptors>
   <class>com.acme.intercept.SecurityInterceptor</class>
   <class>com.acme.intercept.TransactionInterceptor</class>
</interceptors>]]></programlisting> 
            

         </section>

         <section>
            <title>&lt;decorators&gt;</title>

            <para>
               By default, a bean archive has no enabled decorators. A decorator 
               must be explicitly enabled by listing the fully qualified class name in a child &lt;class&gt; element of
               &lt;decorators&gt;.
            </para>
            
            <para>
               There may be zero or more decorator class elements. The order of the class
               declarations determines the decorator ordering. Decorators which occur earlier in the list are called
               first. The same class may not be listed twice. And of course, the class must exist and it must be an
               decorator class.
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<interceptors>
   <class>com.acme.decorate.BigAccountDecorator</class>
   <class>com.acme.decorate.SpecialGiftDecorator</class>
</interceptors>]]></programlisting> 

         </section>

         <section>
            <title>&lt;alternatives&gt;</title>

            <para>
               An alternative is a bean that must be explicitly declared in the beans.xml file if it should be available
               for lookup, injection or EL resolution. By default, a bean archive has no active alternatives. An
               alternative must be explicitly declared using the fully qualified bean class name or stereotype class
               name in either a child &lt;class&gt;
               or &lt;stereotype&gt; element of &lt;alternatives&gt;, respectively.
            </para>
            
            <para>
               An alternative is selected for the bean archive if either: the alternative is a managed bean or session
               bean and the bean class of the bean is listed, or the alternative is a producer method, field or
               resource, and the bean class that declares the method or field is listed, or any
               <literal>@Alternative</literal> stereotype of the alternative is listed.
            </para>

            <para>
               There may be zero or more alternative bean class elements. The same class may not be listed twice. And of
               course, the class must exist and it must be an alternative bean class.
            </para>

            <para>
               There may also be zero or more <literal>@Alternative</literal> stereotype elements. The same stereotype
               may not be listed twice. And of course, the stereotype class must exist and it must be an stereotype
               annotation.
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<stereotypes>
   <class>com.acme.business.MockPaymentProcessor</class>
   <stereotype>com.acme.stereotype.Mock</stereotype>
</stereotypes>]]></programlisting> 

         </section>

         <para>
            And that's it! A very simple schema, used only to activate and order CDI services.
         </para>

      </section>
      

   </section>

   -->
<!--
vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</chapter>
