<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
        "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<chapter id="environments">
    <title>Application servers and environments supported by Weld</title>

    <section>
        <title>Using Weld with JBoss AS</title>

        <para>
            If you are using JBoss AS 6.0, no additional configuration is required to use Weld (or CDI for that matter).
            All you need to do is make your application a bean bean archive by adding
            <literal>META-INF/beans.xml</literal>
            to the classpath or
            <literal>WEB-INF/beans.xml</literal>
            to the web root!
        </para>

        <note>
            <para>
                Additionally, Weld Servlet supports JBoss EAP 5.1, to do this use the
                <literal>jboss5</literal>
                variant
                of Weld Servlet.
            </para>
        </note>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>GlassFish</title>

        <para>
            Weld is also built into GlassFish from V3 onwards. Since GlassFish V3 is the Java EE 6 reference
            implementation, it must support all features of CDI. What better way for GlassFish to support these features
            than to use Weld, the JSR-299 reference implementation? Just package up your CDI application and deploy.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Servlet containers (such as Tomcat or Jetty)</title>

        <para>
            While JSR-299 does not require support for servlet environments, Weld can be used in a servlet container,
            such as Tomcat 6.0 or Jetty 6.1.
        </para>

        <note>
            <para>
                There is a major limitation to using a servlet container. Weld doesn't support deploying session beans,
                injection using
                <literal>@EJB</literal>
                or<literal>@PersistenceContext</literal>, or using transactional
                events in servlet containers. For enterprise features such as these, you should really be looking at a
                Java
                EE application server.
            </para>
        </note>

        <para>
            Weld can be used as a library in an web application that is deployed to a Servlet container. You should
            place
            <literal>weld-servlet.jar</literal>
            within the
            <literal>WEB-INF/lib</literal>
            directory relative to the web
            root.
            <literal>weld-servlet.jar</literal>
            is an "uber-jar", meaning it bundles all the bits of Weld and CDI
            required for running in a Servlet container, for your convenience. Alternatively, you can use its component
            jars. A list of transitive dependencies can be found in the
            <literal>META-INF/DEPENDENCIES.txt</literal>
            file
            inside the
            <literal>weld-servlet.jar</literal>
            artifact.
        </para>

        <para>
            You also need to explicitly specify the servlet listener (used to boot Weld, and control its interaction
            with requests) in
            <literal>WEB-INF/web.xml</literal>
            in the web root:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<listener>
   <listener-class>org.jboss.weld.environment.servlet.Listener</listener-class>
</listener>]]></programlisting>

        <section>
            <title>Tomcat</title>

            <para>
                Tomcat has a read-only JNDI, so Weld can't automatically bind the BeanManager extension SPI. To bind
                the BeanManager into JNDI, you should populate
                <literal>META-INF/context.xml</literal>
                in the web root with
                the following contents:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<Context>
   <Resource name="BeanManager" 
      auth="Container"
      type="javax.enterprise.inject.spi.BeanManager"
      factory="org.jboss.weld.resources.ManagerObjectFactory"/>
</Context>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                and make it available to your deployment by adding this to the bottom of<literal>web.xml</literal>:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<resource-env-ref>
   <resource-env-ref-name>BeanManager</resource-env-ref-name>
   <resource-env-ref-type>
      javax.enterprise.inject.spi.BeanManager
   </resource-env-ref-type>
</resource-env-ref>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Tomcat only allows you to bind entries to<literal>java:comp/env</literal>, so the BeanManager will be
                available at
                <literal>java:comp/env/BeanManager</literal>
            </para>

            <para>
                Weld also supports Servlet injection in Tomcat 6.
            </para>

        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Jetty</title>

            <para>
                Like Tomcat, Jetty has a read-only JNDI, so Weld can't automatically bind the BeanManager. To
                bind the BeanManager to JNDI in Jetty 6, you should populate
                <literal>WEB-INF/jetty-env.xml</literal>
                with
                the following contents:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE Configure PUBLIC "-//Mort Bay Consulting//DTD Configure//EN"
   "http://jetty.mortbay.org/configure.dtd">
<Configure id="webAppCtx" class="org.mortbay.jetty.webapp.WebAppContext">
   <New id="BeanManager" class="org.mortbay.jetty.plus.naming.Resource">
      <Arg><Ref id="webAppCtx"/></Arg> 
      <Arg>BeanManager</Arg>
      <Arg>
         <New class="javax.naming.Reference">
            <Arg>javax.enterprise.inject.spi.BeanManager</Arg> 
            <Arg>org.jboss.weld.resources.ManagerObjectFactory</Arg>
            <Arg/>
         </New>
      </Arg>
   </New>
</Configure>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Jetty 7 has moved to the Eclipse Foundation; if you are using Jetty 7 put the following in your
                <literal>WEB-INF/jetty-env.xml</literal>:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE Configure PUBLIC "-//Mort Bay Consulting//DTD Configure//EN"
   "http://www.eclipse.org/jetty/configure.dtd">

<Configure id="webAppCtx" class="org.eclipse.jetty.webapp.WebAppContext">
    <New id="BeanManager" class="org.eclipse.jetty.plus.jndi.Resource">
        <Arg> <Ref id="webAppCtx"/> </Arg>
        <Arg>BeanManager</Arg>
        <Arg>
            <New class="javax.naming.Reference">
                <Arg>javax.enterprise.inject.spi.BeanManager</Arg>
                <Arg>org.jboss.weld.resources.ManagerObjectFactory</Arg>
                <Arg/>
            </New>
        </Arg>
    </New>
</Configure> ]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Just like in Tomcat, you need to make it available to your deployment by adding this to the bottom of
                <literal>web.xml</literal>:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<resource-env-ref>
   <resource-env-ref-name>BeanManager</resource-env-ref-name>
   <resource-env-ref-type>
      javax.enterprise.inject.spi.BeanManager
   </resource-env-ref-type>
</resource-env-ref>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                Notice that Jetty doesn't not have built-in support for an
                <literal>javax.naming.spi.ObjectFactory</literal>
                like Tomcat, so it's necessary to manually create the
                <literal>javax.naming.Reference</literal>
                to wrap
                around it.
            </para>

            <para>
                Jetty only allows you to bind entries to<literal>java:comp/env</literal>, so the BeanManager will be
                available at
                <literal>java:comp/env/BeanManager</literal>
            </para>

            <para>
                Weld also supports Servlet injection in Jetty 6. To enable this, add the file
                <literal>WEB-INF/jetty-web.xml</literal>
                with the following content to your war:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<!DOCTYPE Configure PUBLIC "-//Mort Bay Consulting//DTD Configure//EN"
   "http://jetty.mortbay.org/configure.dtd">
<Configure id="webAppCtx" class="org.mortbay.jetty.webapp.WebAppContext">
   <Call class="org.jboss.weld.environment.jetty.WeldServletHandler" name="process">
      <Arg><Ref id="webAppCtx"/></Arg>
   </Call>
</Configure>]]></programlisting>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Java SE</title>

        <para>
            In addition to improved integration of the Enterprise Java stack, the "Contexts and Dependency Injection for
            the Java EE platform" specification also defines a state of the art typesafe, stateful dependency injection
            framework, which can prove useful in a wide range of application types. To help developers take advantage of
            this, Weld provides a simple means for being executed in the Java Standard Edition (SE) environment
            independently of any Java EE APIs.
        </para>

        <para>
            When executing in the SE environment the following features of Weld are available:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Managed beans with
                    <literal>@PostConstruct</literal>
                    and
                    <literal>@PreDestroy</literal>
                    lifecycle callbacks
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Dependency injection with qualifiers and alternatives
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <literal>@Application</literal>,
                    <literal>@Dependent</literal>
                    and
                    <literal>@Singleton</literal>
                    scopes
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Interceptors and decorators
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Stereotypes
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Events
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Portable extension support
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
            EJB beans are not supported.
        </para>

        <section id="weld-se">
            <title>CDI SE Module</title>

            <para>
                Weld provides an extension which will boot a CDI bean manager in Java SE, automatically registering all
                simple beans found on the classpath. The command line parameters can be injected using either of the
                following:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Parameters List<String> params;]]></programlisting>

            <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Parameters String[] paramsArray;]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The second form is useful for compatibility with existing classes.
            </para>

            <note>
                <para>
                    The command line parameters do not become available for injection until the
                    <literal>ContainerInitialized</literal>
                    event is fired. If you need access to the parameters during
                    initialization you can do so via the
                    <literal>public static String[] getParameters()</literal>
                    method in
                    <literal>StartMain</literal>.
                </para>
            </note>

            <para>
                Here's an example of a simple CDI SE application:
            </para>

            <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Singleton
public class HelloWorld
{
   public void printHello(@Observes ContainerInitialized event, @Parameters List<String> parameters) {
       System.out.println("Hello " + parameters.get(0));
   }
}]]></programlisting>

        </section>

        <section>

            <title>Bootstrapping CDI SE</title>

            <para>
                CDI SE applications can be bootstrapped in the following ways.
            </para>

            <section>

                <title>The ContainerInitialized Event</title>

                <para>
                    Thanks to the power of CDI's typesafe event model, application developers
                    need not write any bootstrapping code. The Weld SE module comes
                    with a built-in main method which will bootstrap CDI for you and
                    then fire a
                    <literal>ContainerInitialized</literal>
                    event. The entry
                    point for your application code would therefore be a simple bean which observes
                    the
                    <literal>ContainerInitialized</literal>
                    event, as in the previous example.
                </para>

                <para>In this case your application can be started by calling the provided
                    main method like so:
                </para>

                <programlisting role="JAVA">
                    <![CDATA[java org.jboss.weld.environment.se.StartMain <args>]]></programlisting>

            </section>

            <section>

                <title>Programmatic Bootstrap API</title>

                <para>For added flexibility, CDI SE also comes with a bootstrap API
                    which can be called from within your application in order to initialize
                    CDI and obtain references to your application's beans and events. The
                    API consists of two classes:
                    <literal>Weld</literal>
                    and
                    <literal>WeldContainer</literal>.
                </para>

                <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class Weld
{

   /** Boots Weld and creates and returns a WeldContainer instance, through which
    * beans and events can be accesed. */
   public WeldContainer initialize() {...}

   /** Convenience method for shutting down the container. */
   public void shutdown() {...}

}]]></programlisting>

                <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class WeldContainer
{

   /** Provides access to all beans within the application. */
   public Instance<Object> instance() {...}

   /** Provides access to all events within the application. */
   public Event<Object> event() {...}

   /** Provides direct access to the BeanManager. */
   public BeanManager getBeanManager() {...}

}]]></programlisting>

                <para>Here's an example application main method which uses this API
                    to initialize a bean of type<literal>MyApplicationBean</literal>.
                </para>

                <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public static void main(String[] args) {
   WeldContainer weld = new Weld().initialize();
   weld.instance().select(MyApplicationBean.class).get();
   weld.shutdown();
}]]></programlisting>

                <para>Alternatively the application could be started by firing a custom
                    event which would then be observed by another simple bean. The following
                    example fires
                    <literal>MyEvent</literal>
                    on startup.
                </para>

                <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public static void main(String[] args) {
   WeldContainer weld = new Weld().initialize();
   weld.event().select(MyEvent.class).fire( new MyEvent() );
   weld.shutdown();
}]]></programlisting>

            </section>

        </section>

        <section>

            <title>Thread Context</title>

            <para>In contrast to Java EE applications, Java SE applications place no restrictions
                on developers regarding the creation and usage of threads.
                Therefore Weld SE provides a custom scope annotation,<literal>@ThreadScoped</literal>,
                and corresponding context implementation which can be used to bind bean instances
                to the current thread. It is intended to be used in scenarios where you might otherwise
                use<literal>ThreadLocal</literal>, and does in fact use
                <literal>ThreadLocal</literal>
                under the hood.
            </para>

            <para>
                To use the @ThreadScoped annotation you need to enable the
                <literal>RunnableDecorator</literal>
                which 'listens' for all executions of
                <literal>Runnable.run()</literal>
                and
                decorates them by setting up the thread context beforehand, bound to
                the current thread, and destroying the context afterwards.
            </para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<beans>
  <decorators>
     <class>org.jboss.weld.environment.se.threading.RunnableDecorator</class>
  </decorator>
</beans>]]></programlisting>

            <note>
                <para>It is not necessary to use @ThreadScoped in all
                    multithreaded applications. The thread context is not intended
                    as a replacement for defining your own application-specific contexts.
                    It is generally only useful in situations where you would otherwise
                    have used ThreadLocal directly, which are typically rare.
                </para>
            </note>

        </section>

        <section>

            <title>Setting the Classpath</title>

            <para>Weld SE comes packaged as a 'shaded' jar which includes the CDI API,
                Weld Core and all dependant classes bundled into a single jar. Therefore the
                only Weld jar you need on the classpath, in addition to your application's
                classes and dependant jars, is the Weld SE jar. If you are working with a pure
                Java SE application you launch using<literal>java</literal>, this may be simpler
                for you.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you prefer to work with individual dependencies, then you can use the
                <literal>weld-core</literal>
                jar which just contains the Weld SE classes.
                Of course in this mode you will need to assemble the classpath yourself.
                This mode is useful, for example, if you wish to use an alternative slf4j
                log binding.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you work with a dependency management solution such as
                Maven you can declare a dependency on<literal>org.jboss.weld.se:weld-se-core</literal>.
            </para>

        </section>

    </section>

    <!--
    vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
    -->
</chapter>
