<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<chapter id="injection">
   <title>Dependency injection and programmatic lookup</title>

   <para>
      One of the most significant features of CDI&mdash;certainly the most recognized&mdash;is dependency injection;
      excuse me, <emphasis>typesafe</emphasis> dependency injection.
   </para>

   <section>
      <title>Injection points</title>

      <para>
         The <literal>@Inject</literal> annotation lets us define an injection point that is injected during bean 
         instantiation. Injection can occur via three different mechanisms.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         <emphasis>Bean constructor</emphasis> parameter injection:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class Checkout {
        
   private final ShoppingCart cart;
    
   @Inject
   public Checkout(ShoppingCart cart) {
      this.cart = cart;
   }

}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         A bean can only have one injectable constructor.
      </para>

      <para>
         <emphasis>Initializer method</emphasis> parameter injection:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class Checkout {
        
   private ShoppingCart cart;

   @Inject
   void setShoppingCart(ShoppingCart cart) {
      this.cart = cart;
   }
    
}]]></programlisting>

      <note>
         <para>
            A bean can have multiple initializer methods. If the bean is a session bean, the initializer method 
            is not required to be a business method of the session bean.
         </para>
      </note>

      <para>
         And direct field injection:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class Checkout {

   private @Inject ShoppingCart cart;
    
}]]></programlisting>

      <note>
         <para>
            Getter and setter methods are not required for field injection to work (unlike with JSF managed beans).
         </para>
      </note>

      <para>
         Dependency injection always occurs when the bean instance is first instantiated by the container.
         Simplifying just a little, things happen in this order:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               First, the container calls the bean constructor (the default constructor or the one annotated
               <literal>@Inject</literal>), to obtain an instance of the bean.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Next, the container initializes the values of all injected fields of the bean.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Next, the container calls all initializer methods of bean (the call order is not portable, don't 
               rely on it).
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Finally, the <literal>@PostConstruct</literal> method, if any, is called.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>(The only complication is that the container might call initializer methods declared by a superclass 
      before initializing injected fields declared by a subclass.)</para>

      <note>
         <para>
            One major advantage of constructor injection is that it allows the bean to be immutable.
         </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
         CDI also supports parameter injection for some other methods that are invoked by the container. For instance, 
         parameter injection is supported for producer methods:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Produces Checkout createCheckout(ShoppingCart cart) {
    return new Checkout(cart);
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
        This is a case where the <literal>@Inject</literal> annotation <emphasis>is not</emphasis> required at the
        injection point. The same is true for observer methods (which we'll meet in <xref linkend="events"/>) and
        disposer methods.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>What gets injected</title>

      <para>
         The CDI specification defines a procedure, called <emphasis>typesafe resolution</emphasis>, that the container 
         follows when identifying the bean to inject to an injection point.  This algorithm looks complex at first, but 
         once you understand it, it's really quite intuitive. Typesafe resolution is performed at system initialization 
         time, which means that the container will inform the developer immediately if a bean's
         dependencies cannot be satisfied.
      </para>

      <para>
         The purpose of this algorithm is to allow multiple beans to implement the same bean type and either:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               allow the client to select which implementation it requires using a <emphasis>qualifier</emphasis> or
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
               allow the application deployer to select which implementation is appropriate for a particular deployment,
               without changes to the client, by enabling or disabling an <emphasis>alternative</emphasis>, or
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
               allow the beans to be isolated into separate modules.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         Obviously, if you have exactly one bean of a given type, and an injection point with that same type, then bean A is
         going to go into slot A. That's the simplest possible scenario. When you first start your application, you'll
         likely have lots of those.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         But then, things start to get complicated. Let's explore how the container determines which bean to inject in
         more advanced cases. We'll start by taking a closer look at qualifiers.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Qualifier annotations</title>

      <para>
         If we have more than one bean that implements a particular bean type, the injection point can specify exactly
         which bean should be injected using a qualifier annotation. For example, there might be two implementations of
         <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal>:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Synchronous
public class SynchronousPaymentProcessor implements PaymentProcessor {
   public void process(Payment payment) { ... }
}]]></programlisting>      

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Asynchronous
public class AsynchronousPaymentProcessor implements PaymentProcessor {
   public void process(Payment payment) { ... }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Where <literal>@Synchronous</literal> and <literal>@Asynchronous</literal> are qualifier annotations:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Qualifier
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({TYPE, METHOD, FIELD, PARAMETER})
public @interface Synchronous {}]]></programlisting>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Qualifier
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({TYPE, METHOD, FIELD, PARAMETER})
public @interface Asynchronous {}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         A client bean developer uses the qualifier annotation to specify exactly which bean should be injected.
      </para>

      <para>Using field injection:</para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Synchronous PaymentProcessor syncPaymentProcessor;
@Inject @Asynchronous PaymentProcessor asyncPaymentProcessor;]]></programlisting>

      <para>Using initializer method injection:</para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject
public void setPaymentProcessors(@Synchronous PaymentProcessor syncPaymentProcessor, 
                                 @Asynchronous PaymentProcessor asyncPaymentProcessor) {
   this.syncPaymentProcessor = syncPaymentProcessor;
   this.asyncPaymentProcessor = asyncPaymentProcessor;
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>Using constructor injection:</para>

     <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject
public Checkout(@Synchronous PaymentProcessor syncPaymentProcessor, 
                @Asynchronous PaymentProcessor asyncPaymentProcessor) {
   this.syncPaymentProcessor = syncPaymentProcessor;
   this.asyncPaymentProcessor = asyncPaymentProcessor;
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Qualifier annotations can also qualify method arguments of producer, disposer and observer methods. Combining
         qualified arguments with producer methods is a good way to have an implementation of a bean type
         selected at runtime based on the state of the system:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Produces
PaymentProcessor getPaymentProcessor(@Synchronous PaymentProcessor syncPaymentProcessor,
                                     @Asynchronous PaymentProcessor asyncPaymentProcessor) {
   return isSynchronous() ? syncPaymentProcessor : asyncPaymentProcessor;
}]]></programlisting> 
   
      <para>
         If an injected field or a parameter of a bean constructor or initializer method is not explicitly annotated 
         with a qualifier, the default qualifier, <literal>@Default</literal>, is assumed.
      </para>

      <para>
         Now, you may be thinking, <emphasis>"What's the different between using a qualifier and just specifying the
         exact implementation class you want?"</emphasis> It's important to understand that a qualifier is like an
         extension of the interface. It does not create a direct dependency to any particular implementation. There 
         may be multiple alterative implementations of <literal>@Asynchronous PaymentProcessor</literal>!
      </para>

   </section>
   
   <section>
      <title>The built-in qualifiers <literal>@Default</literal> and <literal>@Any</literal></title>
      
      <para>Whenever a bean or injection point does not explicitly declare a qualifier, the container assumes the
      qualifier <literal>@Default</literal>. From time to time, you'll need to decare an injection point without
      specifying a qualifier. There's a qualifier for that too. All beans have the qualifier <literal>@Any</literal>.
      Therefore, by explicitly specifying <literal>@Any</literal> at an injection point, you suppress the default
      qualifier, without otherwise restricting the beans that are eligible for injection.</para>
      
      <para>This is especially useful if you want to iterate over all beans with a certain bean type. For example:</para>
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject 
void initServices(@Any Instance<Service> services) { 
   for (Service service: services) {
      service.init();
   }
}]]></programlisting>
      
   </section>

      <section>
         <title>Qualifiers with members</title>

         <para>
            Java annotations can have members. We can use annotation members to further discriminate a qualifier. This 
            prevents a potential explosion of new annotations. For example, instead of creating several qualifiers 
            representing different payment methods, we could aggregate them into a single annotation with a member:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Qualifier
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({METHOD, FIELD, PARAMETER, TYPE})
public @interface PayBy {
   PaymentMethod value();
}]]></programlisting> 
   
         <para>
            Then we select one of the possible member values when appling the qualifier:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[private @Inject @PayBy(CHECK) PaymentProcessor checkPayment;]]></programlisting> 

         <para>
            We can force the container to ignore a member of a qualifier type by annotating the member 
            <literal>@Nonbinding</literal>.
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Qualifier
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({METHOD, FIELD, PARAMETER, TYPE})
public @interface PayBy {
   PaymentMethod value();
   @Nonbinding String comment() default "";
}]]></programlisting> 

      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Multiple qualifiers</title>

         <para>
            An injection point may specify multiple qualifiers:
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Synchronous @Reliable PaymentProcessor syncPaymentProcessor;]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            Then only a bean which has <emphasis>both</emphasis> qualifier annotations would be eligible for
            injection.
         </para>

         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Synchronous @Reliable
public class SynchronousReliablePaymentProcessor implements PaymentProcessor {
   public void process(Payment payment) { ... }
}]]></programlisting>

      </section>
   
   <section id="alternatives">
      <title>Alternatives</title>
      
      <para>Alternatives are beans whose implementation is specific to a particular client module or deployment
      scenario. This alternative defines a mock implementation of both <literal>@Synchronous PaymentProcessor</literal>
      and <literal>@Asynchronous PaymentProcessor</literal>, all in one:</para>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Alternative @Synchronous @Asynchronous
public class MockPaymentProcessor implements PaymentProcessor {
   public void process(Payment payment) { ... }
}]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>
         By default, <literal>@Alternative</literal> beans are disabled. We need to <emphasis>enable</emphasis> an
         alternative in the <literal>beans.xml</literal> descriptor of a bean archive to make it available for
         instantiation and injection. This activation only applies to the beans in that archive.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<beans
   xmlns="http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="
      http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee
      http://java.sun.com/xml/ns/javaee/beans_1_0.xsd">
   <alternatives>
         <class>org.mycompany.mock.MockPaymentProcessor</class>
   </alternatives>
</beans>]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>
         When an ambiguous dependency exists at an injection point, the container attempts to resolve the ambiguity
         by looking for an enabled alternative among the beans that could be injected. If there is exactly one
         enabled alternative, that's the bean that will be injected.
      </para>
      
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Fixing unsatisfied and ambiguous dependencies</title>
  
      <para>
         The typesafe resolution algorithm fails when, after considering the qualifier annotations on all beans that
         implement the bean type of an injection point and filtering out disabled beans (<literal>@Alternative</literal>
         beans which are not explicitly enabled), the container is unable to identify exactly one bean to inject. The
         container will abort deployment, informing us of the unsatisfied or ambiguous dependency.
      </para>
  
      <para>
         During the course of your development, you're going to encounter this situation. Let's learn how to resolve it.
      </para>
  
      <para>
         To fix an <emphasis>unsatisfied dependency</emphasis>, either: 
      </para>
         
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>      
            <para>
               create a bean which implements the bean type and has all the qualifier types of the injection point,
            </para>
         </listitem> 
         <listitem>
            <para>
               make sure that the bean you already have is in the classpath of the module with the injection point, or
            </para>
         </listitem> 
         <listitem> 
            <para>
               explicitly enable an <literal>@Alternative</literal> bean that implements the bean type and has the 
               appropriate qualifier types, using <literal>beans.xml</literal>.
            </para>
         </listitem> 
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
         To fix an <emphasis>ambiguous dependency</emphasis>, either: 
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>      
            <para>
               introduce a qualifier to distinguish between the two implementations of the bean type, 
            </para>
         </listitem> 
         <listitem>      
            <para>
               disable one of the beans by annotating it <literal>@Alternative</literal>, 
            </para>
         </listitem> 
         <listitem>
            <para>
               move one of the implementations to a module that is not in the classpath of the module with the 
               injection point, or
            </para>
         </listitem> 
         <listitem> 
            <para>
               disable one of two <literal>@Alternative</literal> beans that are trying to occupy the same space, 
               using <literal>beans.xml</literal>.  
            </para>
         </listitem> 
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         See <ulink
         url="http://sfwk.org/Documentation/HowDoAResolveAnAmbiguousResolutionExceptionBetweenAProducerMethodAndARawType">this
         FAQ</ulink> for step-by-step instructions for how to resolve an ambigous resolution exception between a raw
         bean type and a producer method that returns the same bean type.
      </para>
      
      <para>Just remember: "There can be only one."</para>
   
      <para>
         On the other hand, if you really do have an optional or multivalued injection point, you should change
         the type of your injection point to <literal>Instance</literal>, as we'll see in <xref linkend="lookup"/>.
      </para>
  
      <para>
         Now there's one more issue you need to be aware of when using the dependency injection service.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Client proxies</title>
  
      <para>
         Clients of an injected bean do not usually hold a direct reference to a bean instance, unless the bean is
         a dependent object (scope <literal>@Dependent</literal>).
      </para> 
  
      <para>
         Imagine that a bean bound to the application scope held a direct reference to a bean bound to the request
         scope. The application-scoped bean is shared between many different requests. However, each request should see
         a different instance of the request scoped bean&mdash;the current one!
      </para>
  
      <para>
         Now imagine that a bean bound to the session scope holds a direct reference to a bean bound to the application
         scope. From time to time, the session context is serialized to disk in order to use memory more efficiently.
         However, the application scoped bean instance should not be serialized along with the session scoped bean!  It
         can get that reference any time. No need to hoard it!
      </para>
  
      <para>
         Therefore, unless a bean has the default scope <literal>@Dependent</literal>, the container must indirect all
         injected references to the bean through a proxy object. This <emphasis>client proxy</emphasis> is responsible
         for ensuring that the bean instance that receives a method invocation is the instance that is associated with
         the current context. The client proxy also allows beans bound to contexts such as the session context to be
         serialized to disk without recursively serializing other injected beans.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Unfortunately, due to limitations of the Java language, some Java types cannot be proxied by the container. 
         If an injection point declared with one of these types resolves to a bean with any scope other than 
         <literal>@Dependent</literal>, the container will abort deployment, informing us of the problem.
      </para>
  
      <para>The following Java types cannot be proxied by the container:</para>
  
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>classes which don't have a non-private constructor with no parameters, and</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               classes which are declared <literal>final</literal> or have a <literal>final</literal> method,
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>arrays and primitive types.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  
      <para>
         It's usually very easy to fix an unproxyable dependency problem. If an injection point of type
         <literal>X</literal> results in an unproxyable dependency, simply:
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               add a constructor with no parameters to <literal>X</literal>,
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               change the type of the injection point to <literal>Instance&lt;X&gt;</literal>,
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               introduce an interface <literal>Y</literal>, implemented by the injected bean, and change 
               the type of the injection point to <literal>Y</literal>, or
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               if all else fails, change the scope of the injected bean to <literal>@Dependent</literal>.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <note>
      <para>
         A future release of Weld will likely support a non-standard workaround for this limitation, using
         non-portable JVM APIs:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Sun, IcedTea, Mac: <literal>Unsafe.allocateInstance()</literal> (The most efficient)
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               IBM, JRockit: <literal>ReflectionFactory.newConstructorForSerialization()</literal>
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
         But we didn't get around to implementing this yet.
      </para>
      </note>
  
   </section>

   <section id="lookup">

      <title>Obtaining a contextual instance by programmatic lookup</title>

      <para>
         In certain situations, injection is not the most convenient way to obtain a contextual reference. For example,
         it may not be used when:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               the bean type or qualifiers vary dynamically at runtime, or
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               depending upon the deployment, there may be no bean which satisfies the type and qualifiers, or
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               we would like to iterate over all beans of a certain type.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         In these situations, the application may obtain an instance of the interface <literal>Instance</literal>, 
         parameterized for the bean type, by injection:
      </para>
  
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject Instance<PaymentProcessor> paymentProcessorSource;]]></programlisting>
  
      <para>
         The <literal>get()</literal> method of <literal>Instance</literal> produces a contextual instance of the bean.
      </para>
  
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[PaymentProcessor p = paymentProcessorSource.get();]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Qualifiers can be specified in one of two ways:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>by annotating the <literal>Instance</literal> injection point, or</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>by passing qualifiers to the <literal>select()</literal> of <literal>Event</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         Specifying the qualifiers at the injection point is much, much easier:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Asynchronous Instance<PaymentProcessor> paymentProcessorSource;]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>
         Now, the <literal>PaymentProcessor</literal> returned by <literal>get()</literal> will have the qualifier
         <literal>@Asynchronous</literal>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Alternatively, we can specify the qualifier dynamically. First, we add the <literal>@Any</literal> qualifier to
         the injection point, to suppress the default qualifier. (All beans have the qualifier <literal>@Any</literal>.)
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject @Any Instance<PaymentProcessor> paymentProcessorSource;]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>
         Next, we need to obtain an instance of our qualifier type. Since annotatons are interfaces, we can't just write
         <literal>new Asynchronous()</literal>. It's also quite tedious to create a concrete implementation of an annotation 
         type from scratch. Instead, CDI lets us obtain a qualifier instance by subclassing the helper class 
         <literal>AnnotationLiteral</literal>. 
      </para>
      
      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[abstract class AsynchronousQualifier
extends AnnotationLiteral<Asynchronous> implements Asynchronous {}]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         In some cases, we can use an anonymous class:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[PaymentProcessor p = paymentProcessorSource
   .select(new AnnotationLiteral<Asynchronous>() {});]]></programlisting>
   
      <para>
         However, we can't use an anonymous class to implement a qualifier type with members.
      </para>
               
      <para>
         Now, finally, we can pass the qualifier to the <literal>select()</literal> method of <literal>Instance</literal>.
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[Annotation qualifier = synchronously ?
      new SynchronousQualifier() : new AsynchronousQualifier();
PaymentProcessor p = anyPaymentProcessor.select(qualifier).get().process(payment);]]></programlisting> 

   </section>

<section>
  <title>The <literal>InjectionPoint</literal> object</title>
  
  <para>There are certain kinds of dependent objects (beans with scope <literal>@Dependent</literal>) 
  that need to know something about the object or injection point into which they are injected in order 
  to be able to do what they do. For example:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>The log category for a <literal>Logger</literal> depends upon the class of the object 
      that owns it.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Injection of a HTTP parameter or header value depends upon what parameter 
      or header name was specified at the injection point.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Injection of the result of an EL expression evaluation depends upon the 
      expression that was specified at the injection point.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>A bean with scope <literal>@Dependent</literal> may inject an instance of 
  <literal>InjectionPoint</literal> and access metadata relating to the injection point to which 
  it belongs.</para>

  <para>Let's look at an example. The following code is verbose, and vulnerable to refactoring
  problems:</para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[Logger log = Logger.getLogger(MyClass.class.getName());]]></programlisting>

  <para>This clever little producer method lets you inject a JDK <literal>Logger</literal> without 
  explicitly specifying the log category:</para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[class LogFactory {

   @Produces Logger createLogger(InjectionPoint injectionPoint) { 
      return Logger.getLogger(injectionPoint.getMember().getDeclaringClass().getName()); 
   }

}]]></programlisting>

  <para>We can now write:</para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Inject Logger log;]]></programlisting>

  <para>Not convinced? Then here's a second example. To inject HTTP parameters, we need to define 
  a qualifier type:</para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@BindingType
@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({TYPE, METHOD, FIELD, PARAMETER})
public @interface HttpParam {
   @Nonbinding public String value();
}]]></programlisting>

  <para>We would use this qualifier type at injection points as follows:</para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@HttpParam("username") String username;
@HttpParam("password") String password;]]></programlisting>

  <para>The following producer method does the work:</para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[class HttpParams

   @Produces @HttpParam("")
   String getParamValue(InjectionPoint ip) {
      ServletRequest request = (ServletRequest) FacesContext.getCurrentInstance().getExternalContext().getRequest();
      return request.getParameter(ip.getAnnotated().getAnnotation(HttpParam.class).value());
   }

}]]></programlisting>

  <para>Note that acquiring of the request in this example is JSF-centric. For a more generic solution
  you could write your own prodcuer for the request and have it injected as a method parameter.</para>

  <para>Note also that the <literal>value()</literal> member of the <literal>HttpParam</literal>
  annotation is ignored by the container since it is annotated <literal>@Nonbinding.</literal></para>

  <para>The container provides a built-in bean that implements the <literal>InjectionPoint</literal> 
  interface:</para>

<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface InjectionPoint { 
   public Type getType();
   public Set<Annotation> getQualifiers();
   public Bean<?> getBean();
   public Member getMember();
   public Annotated getAnnotated();
   public boolean isDelegate();
   public boolean isTransient();
}]]></programlisting>

</section>

<!--
vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</chapter>
