<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"  [ ]>
<chapter id="next">
   <title>Next steps</title>
  
   <para>
      Because CDI is so new, there's not yet a lot of information available online. That will change over time.
      Regardless, the CDI specification remains the authority for information on CDI. The spec is less than 100 pages and 
      is quite readable (don't worry, it's not like your Blu-ray player manual). Of course, it covers many details we've 
      skipped over here. The spec is available on the
      <ulink url="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=299">JSR-299 page</ulink> at the JCP website.
   </para>
  
   <para>
      The CDI reference implementation, Weld, is being developed at the <ulink url="http://seamframework.org/Weld">Seam
      project</ulink>. The RI development team and the CDI spec lead blog at <ulink
      url="http://in.relation.to">in.relation.to</ulink>. This guide was originally based on a series of blog entries
      published there while the specification was being developed. It's probably the best source of information about
      the future of CDI, Weld and Seam.
   </para>

   <para>
      We encourage you to follow the <ulink url="https://lists.jboss.org/mailman/listinfo/weld-dev">weld-dev</ulink>
      mailing list and to get involved in <ulink url="http://seamframework.org/Weld/Development">development</ulink>. If
      you are reading this guide, you likely have something to offer.
   </para>

   <para>
      We are eager to find volunteers to help revise, proofread or translate this guide. The first step is getting the
      source of this guide checked out. To build against the trunk (latest source), follow these steps:
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Checkout source from <ulink
            url="http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/weld/doc/trunk/reference">http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/weld/doc/trunk/reference</ulink>
            using SVN
         </para>
         <programlisting><![CDATA[$> svn co http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/weld/doc/trunk/reference weld-reference]]></programlisting> 
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Edit the <literal>pom.xml</literal> file in the root of the checkout and remove the "<literal>-SNAPSHOT</literal>" 
            from the version element (so you don't have to build other Weld modules).
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Build using Maven 2
         </para>
         <programlisting><![CDATA[$> mvn]]></programlisting> 
         <note>
            <para>
               If you experience an out of memory error, try setting this environment variable:
               <literal>MAVEN_OPTS=-Xmx1024m</literal>
            </para>
         </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>The PDF version of the reference guide will appear the current directory. You can find the HTML version
         in <literal>target/docbook/publish/en-US/html</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>
      We look forward to your participation! 
   </para>

<!--
vim:et:ts=3:sw=3:tw=120
-->
</chapter>
